<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Generated by argml-converter skill on 2026-05-12 against ArgML spec v0.2.
     Draft — review before use.

     Note: this exact post is the running example in the ArgML 0.2 spec
     (notably Appendix B). Where the spec assigns canonical ids and markup
     for specific passages, this conversion uses those ids verbatim. The
     rest of the post is marked up consistent with the spec's pattern.

     Orphan: footnote 5 in the source has no inline reference marker; it
     is preserved as a <note> at the close of the "Phenomena are Intrinsic"
     section, where its content (illusionists and semantic distinctions)
     is most relevant. -->

<post xmlns="urn:argml:v1" id="morality-without-consciousness"
      conforms-to="urn:argml:spec:v0.2">

  <head>
    <metadata>
      <title>Morality without Consciousness</title>
      <author>IanWS</author>
      <date>2026-04-17</date>
      <source>https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/bWuhKA8bhsPGN7zRJ/morality-without-consciousness</source>
    </metadata>

    <provenance>
      <generator id="g-author" type="human" who="IanWS"
                 date="2026-04-17" role="original-author"/>
      <generator id="g-extractor" type="llm" model="claude-opus-4.7"
                 date="2026-05-12" role="extractor"/>
    </provenance>

    <imports>
      <import prefix="linch"
              doc="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/qfitpqvQzeZy2mSGi/the-fourth-world"/>
      <import prefix="seq"
              doc="https://www.lesswrong.com/s/FqgKAHZAiZn9JAjDo"/>
      <import prefix="sep" doc="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/"/>
    </imports>

    <terms>
      <term id="consciousness" canonical="sep:consciousness" provenance="g-extractor">
        <gloss>Phenomenal consciousness — the "hard problem", qualia.</gloss>
        <alias>phenomenal consciousness</alias>
        <alias>qualia</alias>
        <alias>the hard problem</alias>
        <alias>phenomena</alias>
        <alias>phenomenal experience</alias>
      </term>
      <term id="physicalism" canonical="sep:physicalism" provenance="g-extractor">
        <gloss>The thesis that everything that exists is physical, or supervenes on the physical.</gloss>
      </term>
      <term id="dualism" canonical="sep:dualism" provenance="g-extractor">
        <gloss>The thesis that the mental and the physical are fundamentally distinct.</gloss>
      </term>
      <term id="illusionism"
            canonical="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/qualia/#IllAboQua"
            provenance="g-extractor">
        <gloss>The view that phenomenal consciousness is an illusion — what we report as qualia are functional states that lack phenomenal properties.</gloss>
      </term>
      <term id="preference" scope="local" provenance="g-extractor">
        <gloss>An entity's expressed interest counter to the second law of thermodynamics.</gloss>
      </term>
      <term id="epiphenomenalism" canonical="sep:epiphenomenalism" provenance="g-extractor">
        <gloss>The view that mental phenomena are causally inert byproducts of physical processes.</gloss>
      </term>
      <term id="mysticism" scope="local" provenance="g-extractor">
        <gloss>Any explanation for consciousness that departs so far from a conventional understanding of reality as to render an expansion of the term "physicalism" meaningless — e.g., consciousness as the soul.</gloss>
      </term>
    </terms>

    <assumptions>
      <assumption id="A1" provenance="g-author">
        I have phenomenal experience.
      </assumption>
    </assumptions>

    <takeaways>
      <takeaway ref="C6.7" priority="primary" provenance="g-extractor"/>
      <takeaway ref="C4.9" priority="secondary" provenance="g-extractor"/>
      <takeaway ref="C3.6" priority="load-bearing" provenance="g-extractor"/>
    </takeaways>
  </head>

  <body>

    <!-- ============================================================== -->
    <!-- Intro (no heading in source)                                   -->
    <!-- ============================================================== -->

    <p>A recent post by <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/users/linch">@Linch</a>, "<a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/qfitpqvQzeZy2mSGi/the-fourth-world">The Fourth World</a>," <claim id="L0" mode="attributed" attributed-to="Linch"
           source="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/qfitpqvQzeZy2mSGi/the-fourth-world"
           same-as="linch:fourth-world-thesis"
           provenance="g-extractor">gets at an important implication of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>— namely, that we ought to suspect further aspects of reality than we can today observe</claim>—but I'm not sure it arrives there the right way, or that it derives the correct conclusions.<note provenance="g-extractor">In the author's defense, in a footnote they clarify that they are "not that interested in the difference between whether these worlds are truly different or just conceptually interesting ways to talk about things." But the post's arguments rely heavily on the reality of this difference, so I will address it anyways.</note></p>

    <p>The author makes two assumptions in his post which ought not to come for free. Firstly, <claim id="L1" mode="attributed" attributed-to="Linch"
           source="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/qfitpqvQzeZy2mSGi/the-fourth-world"
           same-as="linch:no-physicalism"
           provenance="g-extractor">the author assumes that we could not explain <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> through <term ref="physicalism">physicalism</term></claim>. This is already a strong claim, one with which about half of surveyed philosophers disagree.<evidence type="survey" ref="https://survey2020.philpeople.org" provenance="g-extractor">In the 2020 PhilPapers Survey, 51.93% of respondents accepted or leaned toward physicalism about the mind, while 32.08% favored non-physicalism. See Bourget, D. &amp; Chalmers, D. J., "Philosophers on Philosophy: The 2020 PhilPapers Survey."</evidence> Secondly, <claim id="L2" mode="attributed" attributed-to="Linch"
           source="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/qfitpqvQzeZy2mSGi/the-fourth-world"
           same-as="linch:consciousness-as-moral-basis"
           provenance="g-extractor">the author assumes that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is the basis for morality, or that our moral obligations are primarily due toward conscious beings</claim>.</p>

    <p>I think this second assumption is particularly common. At a recent meetup, I heard a participant complain that it is really hard to talk about <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, because we are always tying up <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> with morality. <claim id="C1.0" mode="asserted" credence="speculative" provenance="g-extractor">I suspect this happens because we sneak in non-<term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> assumptions about <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> into discussions about morality.</claim></p>

    <p><claim id="C1.1" mode="asserted"
              supports="L0" attacks="L1 L2"
              credence="confident" provenance="g-extractor">So, I would like to defend the author's claim that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> ought to cause us to suppose further unobserved aspects of reality (which could be very different from the reality we know), while also defending a purely <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> explanation for <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, and decoupling <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> from morality.</claim> I will continue to respond to specific arguments in "The Fourth World," though my goal is to articulate my own, positive argument, rather than critique the post.</p>

    <p>Throughout, whenever I refer to "<term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>" without a qualifier, I am referring to <term ref="consciousness">phenomenal consciousness</term>, or the "<term ref="consciousness">hard problem</term>" of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, or <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term>. I'll use words like "cognition" or "neurophysiology" to refer to non-phenomenal processes, which we typically understand as explainable by modern neuroscience, even if imperfectly. <claim id="C1.2" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">The distinction is important, as we otherwise backdoor capabilities like judgment and agency into <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> without sufficient justification.</claim> <claim id="C1.3" mode="asserted" credence="tentative" supports="C1.1" provenance="g-extractor">I believe this is the crux of <em>why</em> so many of us intuit <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> as a prerequisite for morality, when I think it is very possibly not the case.</claim></p>

    <!-- ============================================================== -->
    <section id="s-dualism-as-semantics">
      <heading level="1">Dualism as Semantics</heading>

      <p><em>Check out the <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/s/FqgKAHZAiZn9JAjDo">basic case for <term ref="physicalism">physicalism</term></a> if you haven't already. I might repeat some arguments for <term ref="physicalism">physicalism</term> through this post, but I won't make a full, bottom-up argument.</em></p>

      <p><claim id="L3" mode="attributed" attributed-to="Linch"
                source="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/qfitpqvQzeZy2mSGi/the-fourth-world"
                same-as="linch:three-domains"
                provenance="g-extractor">The author introduces us to his fourth world by supposing three distinct domains to reality: the physical world, the mathematical world, and <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>.</claim> <claim id="L4" mode="attributed" attributed-to="Linch"
                source="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/qfitpqvQzeZy2mSGi/the-fourth-world"
                same-as="linch:robot-civilization"
                provenance="g-extractor">The author later claims that a non-conscious, robot civilization would never suspect <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> exists.</claim></p>

      <p><claim id="C2.0" mode="asserted" credence="speculative" provenance="g-extractor">I surmise the author is pointing at some kind of <term ref="dualism">dualism</term>, with mathematics and logic being a third, metaphysical entity.</claim> <claim id="C2.1" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">The difficulty with <term ref="dualism">dualist</term> claims is that they either rely on a "<term ref="mysticism">mystical</term>," non-physical substance, or they rely on semantic qualifications for the physical world.</claim></p>

      <argument mode="case" id="A-case-soul" supports="C2.2" provenance="g-extractor">
        <p>For example, let us suppose that we learn <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is actually the emergence of a soul, dipping its head in from some heavenly plane of existence. We learn that all our physical laws are arbitrary and completely determined by the whim of God. In this extreme scenario, do we then accept <term ref="dualism">dualism</term>?</p>
      </argument>

      <argument mode="case" id="A-case-higher-dim" supports="C2.2" provenance="g-extractor">
        <p>Let's reframe the question. Let us suppose instead that we learn <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is the emergence of higher dimensional reality within our own. That higher dimensional reality determines all the physical laws of our known universe. In this scenario, do we accept <term ref="dualism">dualism</term>, or merely expand our definition of physics to account for our new knowledge of reality?</p>
      </argument>

      <inference id="I-2.2-cases"
                 from="A-case-soul A-case-higher-dim" to="C2.2"
                 pattern="argument-by-cases"
                 defeasible="true" strength="strong"
                 provenance="g-extractor"/>

      <p><claim id="C2.2" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">My point is that nearly all explanations for <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> ought to collapse towards <term ref="physicalism">physicalism</term>, because any fundamental discoveries required to explain <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> also compel us to redefine physics accordingly.</claim> <claim id="C2.3" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">I will retain the term "<term ref="mysticism">mysticism</term>" for any explanations that depart so far from a conventional understanding of reality as to render an expansion of the term "<term ref="physicalism">physicalism</term>" meaningless, i.e. if <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is actually the soul.</claim> So, we could concede <term ref="dualism">dualism</term> for the first example, but we ought to stick to <term ref="physicalism">physicalism</term> for the second.</p>

      <p><claim id="C2.4" mode="asserted"
                attacks="L4" attack-type="undermine"
                rests-on="C2.2" credence="considered"
                provenance="g-extractor">If we accept a <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> explanation of <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> as at least <em>possible</em>, then we should not assume a robot civilization could never discover <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>.</claim> We have no way to observe or infer <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> today, but if <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> exists in physical reality, then it at least seems it <em>might</em> be possible. Without a scientific explanation for the <term ref="consciousness">hard problem of consciousness</term>, it is premature to rule this out.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================== -->
    <section id="s-phenomena-are-intrinsic">
      <heading level="1">Phenomena are Intrinsic</heading>

      <p>Aside from a <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> or <term ref="mysticism">mystic</term> explanation for <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, we could also suppose that <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> do not exist at all, or that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is an illusion.<note provenance="g-extractor">A few days before I finalized this post, Tenobrus wrote an <a href="https://x.com/tenobrus/status/2044671918109048876">article on X</a> that might serve as a popular example of this view. Daniel Dennett's "<a href="https://web.ics.purdue.edu/~drkelly/DennettQuiningQualia1988.pdf">Quining Qualia</a>" is a foundational text here.</note> <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/qualia/#IllAboQua"><term ref="illusionism">Illusionism</term></a> is a highly counterintuitive stance, given we all have the vivid impression of our own <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> (how do you convince someone that they do not actually perceive the "redness of red"?). In some sense, our subjective experience is the <em>only</em> thing we know (cf. solipsism), so it seems really weird to claim it does not actually exist.</p>

      <!-- Reductio: no <argument> wrapping needed; pattern on the
           inference carries the structure. -->
      <claim id="C3.1-supposition" mode="supposed" provenance="g-extractor">
        Strong <term ref="illusionism">illusionism</term> is correct: there is no <term ref="consciousness">phenomenal experience</term>.
      </claim>

      <claim id="C3.1-target" mode="reductio-target" provenance="g-extractor">
        We are all already zombies (I experience, yet sadly I do not exist).
      </claim>

      <inference id="I-3.1-reductio"
                 from="C3.1-supposition A1" to="C3.1-target"
                 pattern="reductio-ad-absurdum"
                 defeasible="false" strength="deductive"
                 provenance="g-extractor">
        Strong <term ref="illusionism">illusionism</term> entails we lack <term ref="consciousness">phenomenal experience</term>. A1 asserts <term ref="consciousness">phenomenal experience</term> as foundational. Contradiction.
      </inference>

      <p><claim id="C3.1" mode="asserted" rests-on="A1"
                attacks="C3.1-supposition" attack-type="rebut"
                via="I-3.1-reductio"
                credence="confident" provenance="g-extractor">Our experience of existence <em>is</em> phenomenal, so I don't see a way to refute the <term ref="consciousness">hard problem</term> without asserting we are all already zombies (I experience, yet sadly I do not exist).</claim> This is contrary to my own axiomatic belief that I experience existence, so I don't see any way to proceed further with a strong <term ref="illusionism">illusionist</term> argument. If you choose a different axiom, well, ok.</p>

      <p><claim id="C3.2" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">But <term ref="illusionism">illusionism</term> is right to question what and when something is actually phenomenal.</claim> In other words, I find it weird to refute <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term>, but legitimate to debate the <em>scope</em> of <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term>. <claim id="C3.3" mode="asserted" credence="considered" supports="C3.6" provenance="g-extractor">Because when referring to <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, we are often actually referring to the reactive and evaluative machinery <em>behind</em> <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, e.g. cognition, and not to <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> themselves.</claim></p>

      <p>Consider our phenomenal experience of pain. We generally dislike pain, and indeed many ethical frameworks take for granted that we ought to minimize suffering. But why? When we say pain is bad, are we evaluating a distinct "quale of pain" as bad, or are we reacting negatively to the neurophysiological process of pain?</p>

      <p><claim id="C3.4" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">I'll refer to this as the difference between an <em>extrinsic</em> and <em>intrinsic</em> interpretation of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>. If we take a <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> position of the <term ref="consciousness">hard problem of consciousness</term>, then we can suppose <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> are either <em>intrinsic</em> in neurophysiological processes in a way that we do not yet understand, or that <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> are <em>extrinsic</em> to neurophysiological processes.</claim> In other words, is there a property of neurophysiology that we cannot yet quantify (like weight) or are there entities extrinsic to our neurophysiological makeup that we have not yet discovered (like a particle).</p>

      <p><claim id="C3.4.1" mode="asserted" credence="tentative" supports="C3.6" provenance="g-extractor">My reading of the dominant theories of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> (e.g., IIT, Global Workspace Theory) is that they lean toward an intrinsic view.</claim> Essentially, there is something about our neurophysiology that just <em>does</em> induce <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term>. The two are inseparable, <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> just <em>are</em> a property of some neurophysiological processes. We don't know yet what something is, though it might involve <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DI6Hu-DhQwE">weird fundamental physics</a>. In this view, there is no sense in talking about a phenomenon of pain <em>separate</em> from the underlying neurophysiological activity, in the same way it does not make sense to discuss weight separate from gravity or mass.</p>

      <argument mode="thought-experiment" id="A-c-particle"
                supports="C3.5" provenance="g-extractor">
        <p>For an extrinsic example, imagine that there was an undetected particle of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, the c-particle, which somehow interacted with neurophysiological processes, or were produced by them. <term ref="consciousness">Phenomena</term> are actually composed of c-particles. We might further suppose that c-particles come in many flavors. There is a c-particle of pain, a c-particle of happiness, etc. Or perhaps they're just different arrangements of c-particles, who knows! Mental states, as we understand them, are actually determined by c-particles. Unlike with an intrinsic view of <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term>, it actually <em>is</em> coherent to discuss pain separate from the underlying neurophysiology. We just need the right c-particles.</p>
      </argument>

      <p>I have admittedly chosen a silly example for an extrinsic view of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>; I imagine few would argue for an actual "c-particle." But <claim id="C3.5" mode="asserted" credence="confident" provenance="g-extractor">any extrinsic view will require a mysterious "something else" to explain <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, which must then causally interact with our neurophysiology, unless we are willing to accept <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> as a mere <term ref="epiphenomenalism">epiphenomenal</term> side-effect.</claim><note provenance="g-extractor">I suspect one reason some people cling to an extrinsic view of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is that they want to retain a black box for "free will" to drive decisions.</note></p>

      <p>It would be wrong to claim either of these theories are "correct." As <term ref="physicalism">physicalists</term>, we have to accept this as a question for science, and in reality, <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> may not fit so neatly into my intrinsic/extrinsic divide. But <claim id="C3.6" mode="asserted" via="I-3.1"
                credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">I still find it much more <em>likely</em> that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is somehow intrinsic to neurophysiology.</claim> <claim id="C3.7" mode="asserted" supports="C3.6" credence="confident" provenance="g-extractor">An intrinsic theory requires less deviation from contemporary neuroscience, as we don't have to posit that neuroscience is somehow insufficient to explain mental processes (no c-particles intervene)</claim>, and <claim id="C3.8" mode="asserted" supports="C3.6" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">we can neatly sidestep some of the problems of <term ref="epiphenomenalism">epiphenomenalism</term> (certain mental states are intrinsically experiential)</claim>.</p>

      <inference id="I-3.1" from="C3.5 C3.7 C3.8" to="C3.6"
                 scheme="inference-to-best-explanation"
                 pattern="conjunction-of-premises"
                 defeasible="true" strength="moderate"
                 provenance="g-extractor"/>

      <p><claim id="C3.9" mode="asserted" rests-on="C3.6"
                credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">So, if we suppose an intrinsic, <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> theory of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, then our experience of pain is by definition <em>inseparable</em> from the pain reaction itself. It is, in fact, <em>nonsensical</em> to discuss an experience of pain distinct from the neurophysiological activity associated with pain. That is pain; the thing itself <em>is</em> the neurophysiology!</claim></p>

      <p><claim id="C3.10" mode="asserted" supports="C3.6" credence="tentative" provenance="g-extractor">I suspect <term ref="illusionism">illusionism</term> is right that there is nothing like a c-particle.</claim> <claim id="C3.11" mode="asserted" credence="considered" rests-on="C3.6" provenance="g-extractor">There is no independent experience or <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term> of a good cup of coffee—there is only the experience of our own neurophysiology tasting the coffee and evaluating it as good. <term ref="consciousness">Consciousness</term> itself is not responsible for judgment and evaluations—that work is all done by the mechanics of neurophysiology. <term ref="consciousness">Consciousness</term> does not "intervene" to make its own decisions.</claim></p>

      <!-- Footnote 5 in source has no inline reference marker; placed
           here as the orphan content is about illusionism. -->
      <note status="orphan-footnote" provenance="g-extractor">My personal opinion is that <term ref="illusionism">illusionists</term>, like Daniel Dennett, do sometimes rely on tricks of semantic distinctions to make claims against <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term>, the same way Chalmers does to make non-<term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> explanations for <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>.</note>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================== -->
    <section id="s-generalizing-ethics-with-preferences">
      <heading level="1">Generalizing Ethics with Preferences</heading>

      <p><claim id="C4.0" mode="asserted" credence="tentative" provenance="g-extractor">I'd now like to consider the ethics downstream of a <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term>, intrinsic understanding of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>. Namely, if <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is intrinsic to neurophysiological activity, then why should ethics fix itself on the conscious aspects of that activity? Is this not an arbitrary distinction? Should we not rather respect the <em><term ref="preference">preferences</term></em> those activities represent?</claim></p>

      <p><claim id="C4.1" mode="asserted" credence="speculative" provenance="g-extractor">I suspect that <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term>, as intrinsic properties of neurophysiology, are undifferentiated.</claim> A chair and an apple have different weights, but we don't distinguish the weight of furniture from the weight of fruit. Similarly, our experience of pain and happiness may <em>feel</em> different, and may correspond to different biological states, but both experiences are ultimately "just" <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term>, distinguished thanks to our mental capacities. I would guess that the same is true even of sensory <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term>, like the "redness of red."</p>

      <p>If all this seems highly speculative, then let me simply state that <claim id="C4.2" mode="asserted" credence="considered" supports="C4.5" provenance="g-extractor">no phenomenon seems to me inherently good or bad. Experiencing happiness is distinct from experiencing happiness as good.</claim> Now, there might be something about e.g. dopamine that causes me to <em>want</em> more happiness. But that is a consequence of my neurophysiology, it is one of the reasons I experience happiness as good. It's not a quality of my experience of happiness (the phenomenon of happiness) itself.</p>

      <p><claim id="O4.0" mode="anticipated-objection"
                attacks="C4.2" attack-type="rebut"
                provenance="g-extractor">Perhaps one could object that there is no experience of happiness without wanting happiness to continue, or no experience of suffering without wanting suffering to stop; that the mental state cannot be differentiated from its reaction.</claim> <claim id="C4.3" mode="asserted"
                attacks="O4.0" attack-type="undercut"
                credence="considered" supports="C4.0"
                provenance="g-extractor">But is this not just another reason to focus on the reaction, or the expressed <term ref="preference">preference</term>, rather than the experience itself?</claim></p>

      <p>The distinction I'm trying to make may be irrelevant when discussing humans, who have well understood <term ref="preference">preferences</term> for different mental states. But we have to be very precise if we would like to generalize moral principles to non-human intelligence.</p>

      <argument mode="thought-experiment" id="A-alien-goo"
                supports="C4.5" provenance="g-extractor">
        <p>Let's suppose we are visited by a highly developed species of alien goo. We suppose the aliens are somehow biological, but it's unclear! The aliens are very different from us. The aliens also have the strange habit of climbing to the tallest point in any room they enter. If for any reason the aliens cannot reach the tallest point, as in when they are restrained, the alien goo begins to vibrate. When released, the alien quickly proceeds to climb to the tallest point in the room.</p>

        <p>Now, imagine the aliens are observing your living room. The aliens are very bad at detecting electromagnetic radiation and mostly observe the world through touch and vibration. The aliens are very interested in your potted plant, which slowly adjusts its leaves over the course of the day. The aliens can't tell that the plant is adjusting to the sunlight. They just observe that the plant always closes up its leaves for half the day.</p>

        <p>Question: Without any further information, do we have a moral obligation to allow the alien to climb to the highest point in our room? Does the alien have a moral obligation to allow the plant to close its leaves?</p>
      </argument>

      <p>Ultimately the answer will depend on your moral framework. But <claim id="C4.5" mode="asserted" via="I-3.1"
                credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">if you would agree that we have a moral obligation not to cause an alien pain, then I think you should say yes, we are both morally obliged to allow the observed entity to act according to their inferred <term ref="preference">preference</term></claim>.</p>

      <p>In both scenarios, the observed entity exhibits a clear <term ref="preference">preference</term>. The alien always wants to climb as high as possible. The plant always wants to open and close its leaves. We don't have any clear idea of whether the entities in question are conscious. But why would this matter? <term ref="consciousness">Consciousness</term> is intrinsic to some unknown subset of entities in the universe. Neither we nor the alien can detect whether an entity is conscious. But we <em>do</em> know that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> has always corresponded with the expression of <term ref="preference">preferences</term>.</p>

      <p><claim id="O4.1" mode="anticipated-objection"
                attacks="C4.5" attack-type="undercut"
                provenance="g-extractor">You might be thinking that the real difference is the plant's response to light is entirely automatic, while we are deeply cognitive agents. You can't compare our <term ref="preference">preferences</term> to those of a plant!</claim> <claim id="C4.7" mode="asserted"
                attacks="O4.1" attack-type="undercut"
                credence="tentative" provenance="g-extractor">But I think this overlooks how dumbly reactive a lot of <term ref="preference">preferences</term> are, even if they are unclearly expressed.</claim> If you poke me with a needle, I will want you to stop, even if I keep a straight face. I don't have very much control over my pain response. It just happens!</p>

      <p><claim id="C4.6" mode="asserted" credence="tentative" supports="C4.5" provenance="g-extractor">We might qualify that a <term ref="preference">preference</term> should represent an entity's interests counter to the second law of thermodynamics.</claim> A rolling stone does not represent a <term ref="preference">preference</term>. However, if it began to roll uphill, it would!</p>

      <p><claim id="O4.2" mode="anticipated-objection"
                attacks="C4.5" attack-type="rebut"
                provenance="g-extractor">I anticipate several counterarguments to a naïve definition of <term ref="preference">preference</term>, with potentially absurd conclusions. For example, suppose the alien also noticed your rotating fan. Wouldn't the alien have to suppose a moral obligation to the fan as well? And how do we avoid moral equivalences between turning off a fan and trimming a plant and killing a person?</claim></p>

      <p><claim id="C4.8" mode="asserted"
                attacks="O4.2" attack-type="undercut"
                credence="tentative" provenance="g-extractor">These are legitimate lines of critique that a moral framework using <term ref="preference">preference</term> as the qualifier for moral obligation would have to answer. But it's easy to imagine different mechanisms to do this, such as by defining some heuristic for the "strength" of <term ref="preference">preference</term>, similar to the way utilitarianism thinks about utility, or looking at the reversibility of decisions.</claim> I'm also not trying to argue for some sort of cosmic libertarianism. The practice of ethics is inevitably messy, with lots of confusing gray areas. A good follow-up would be to evaluate a full moral system based on <term ref="preference">preference</term>, maybe trying to stress test a few repurposed moral imperatives in a system that made no assumptions about <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>. However, <claim id="C4.9" mode="asserted" credence="tentative"
                provenance="g-extractor">I am optimistic that in every instance where one might be tempted to evaluate ethics on the basis of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, one could instead insert <term ref="preference">preference</term>.</claim></p>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================== -->
    <section id="s-an-unobserved-reality">
      <heading level="1">An Unobserved Reality</heading>

      <p>I accept that you might find my argument for <term ref="preference">preferences</term> insufficient, either because an ethical system for <term ref="preference">preference</term> is not yet defined, or because you believe that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> itself is very special. Though a <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> should wonder <em>why</em> <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is restricted to the mind, it's certainly the popular consensus.</p>

      <p><claim id="C5.0" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">What I question is how one can be confident that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is unique?</claim> <claim id="C5.1" mode="asserted" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">We already know there is at least <em>one</em> aspect to reality that is utterly unobservable to an outsider. We would have no concept of <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> if it were not for our own minds.</claim> <claim id="C5.2" mode="asserted"
                supports="L0" credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">Is this not the best possible evidence that there might be <em>other</em> aspects of reality we cannot observe?</claim></p>

      <p>This is what "The Fourth World" gets right. <claim id="C5.3" mode="asserted" supports="L0"
                credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">Though why limit ourselves to a "fourth" world? For all we know, there might be <em>infinitely</em> many aspects of reality that we cannot observe today, or which may be fundamentally unobservable.</claim> Like the author, I find this incredibly exciting.</p>

      <p><claim id="C5.4" mode="asserted"
                attacks="L2" attack-type="undermine"
                rests-on="C5.2" credence="considered"
                provenance="g-extractor">But these tremendous unknowns as to the nature of reality should give us pause before rating <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> as unique and morally important.</claim></p>

      <p>Let's consider a speculative example, meant to demonstrate the logical possibility of alternatives to <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> in a <term ref="physicalism">physicalist</term> universe.</p>

      <argument mode="thought-experiment" id="A-qualia-counter"
                supports="C5.5" provenance="g-extractor">
        <p>Returning to our earlier alien scenario, let's pretend we have uncovered the physical substrate for <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>. In fact, it's now relatively easy to purchase <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term> counters, which, functioning similar to a Geiger counter, allow us to estimate the "amount" of <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> in an entity. Holding our <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term> counter up to the alien goo, we fail to detect any <term ref="consciousness">phenomenal consciousness</term>!</p>

        <p>However, the aliens have their own device. The alien physiology somehow fails to produce <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, but it <em>does</em> involve some other, mysterious aspect of reality… say, "monads." And lowering a "monad" counter down to us, the aliens fail to detect a single one.</p>
      </argument>

      <p><claim id="C5.5" mode="asserted"
                attacks="L2" attack-type="undermine"
                credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">If we accept there could be <em>further</em> aspects of reality that we cannot observe, not unlike <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, then we should not take for granted that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is privileged among intelligent beings.</claim> I understand this is very weird to consider, but I do not think it is any weirder than the <term ref="consciousness">hard problem of consciousness</term> is already. Our example is similar to Nagel's famous "What it's like to be a …" thought experiment, with the additional caveat that we swap out <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> itself for some new, unknown aspect of reality. Rather than ask what it is like to experience the <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term> of a bat with a bat's cognition, we ask what it is like to have the "monads" of an alien goo with an alien goo's cognition (where "monads" are strictly different from <term ref="consciousness">qualia</term>).</p>

      <p>All the standard caveats that conceivability does not mean reality apply. But <claim id="C5.6" mode="asserted"
                supports="C5.5" credence="tentative"
                scheme="argument-from-example"
                provenance="g-extractor">given the existing evidence for alternative paths to cognition from terrestrial neurophysiology (e.g. machine intelligence), we ought to consider seriously whether there might be alternatives to <term ref="consciousness">phenomena</term> <em>like</em> <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, but substantively different.</claim></p>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================== -->
    <section id="s-recap">
      <heading level="1">Recap</heading>

      <p>To summarize my argument:</p>

      <p>1. <claim id="C6.1" mode="restated" same-as="C1.1"
                   credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor"><term ref="physicalism">Physicalism</term> is a popular and reasonable explanation of <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>.</claim></p>

      <p>2. <claim id="C6.2" mode="restated" same-as="C3.6"
                   supports="C6.3" credence="considered"
                   provenance="g-extractor">A <term ref="physicalism">physicalist's</term> best guess should be that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is somehow intrinsic to neurophysiology, otherwise we have to make strange ontological and scientific conclusions (like c-particles).</claim></p>

      <p>3. <claim id="C6.3" mode="asserted"
                   rests-on="C3.6" supports="C6.4"
                   credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">Once we assume <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> is physically intrinsic to the neurophysiological process itself, it is no longer necessary to assume moral obligations to one aspect of that process.</claim></p>

      <p>4. <claim id="C6.4" mode="asserted"
                   credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">We should instead assess moral obligations to the <term ref="preference">preferences</term> exhibited by neurophysiology. Presumably, we also owe some obligations to any agent which exhibits <term ref="preference">preferences</term>, but this is the responsibility of a moral framework to judge.</claim></p>

      <p>5. <claim id="C6.5" mode="anticipated-objection"
                   attacks="C6.4" attack-type="undercut"
                   provenance="g-extractor">One can try to defend an obligation to <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> by asserting it is special.</claim></p>

      <p>6. <claim id="C6.6" mode="restated" same-as="C5.2"
                   attacks="C6.5" attack-type="undermine"
                   supports="L0" credence="considered"
                   provenance="g-extractor">However, if we cannot observe <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>, we ought to suppose there could be further aspects of reality we cannot observe, similar or dissimilar to <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> in ways we do not yet understand.</claim></p>

      <p>7. It is conceptually possible to imagine beings very different from ourselves whose cognition involves these unknown aspects of reality. So, <claim id="C6.7" mode="restated" same-as="C4.9"
                   credence="tentative" provenance="g-extractor">it would be premature to determine that <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term> demands unique obligations.</claim></p>

      <p><claim id="C-concession" mode="conceded"
                credence="considered" provenance="g-extractor">Obviously, these final conclusions are several steps removed from ground truth.</claim> However, I have tried to surface the implications of what I assess to be the most likely explanations for <term ref="consciousness">phenomenal consciousness</term>. For better or worse, a lot of beliefs are downstream of our explanations for <term ref="consciousness">consciousness</term>. While the <term ref="consciousness">hard problem</term> remains unsolved, it would be good to continue exploring the ethical implications of different theories.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</post>